American Philosophical Society Archives. Record Group IIj. 1898-1984 APS.Archives.IIj APS.Archives.IIj
American Philosophical Society
- Papers
  - Receipt for parcel taken on board the brig Liberty and forwarded to John Vaughan., Undated; 2-1/2x7; Paddock, Daniel
    D.S. 1p.
  - Letter to John Vaughan, Undated; 6" x 7 3/4"; Patterson, Robert M. (Robert Maskell), 1787-1854
    [Philadelphia], n.d. 2pp. and address. A.Com.I. Note on the history of the building in Centre Square to be used as an observatory.
  - Plan of a German railroad, Undated; American Philosophical Society.
  - Abstract of the prospectus:, Undated; 6 1/2" x 9 3/4"; Rosellini, Ippolito, 1800-1843
    Monuments of Egypt and Nubia, London, n. d. 2pp. Pr. D. (In Italian and English.) Enclosed in: Peter S. Duponceau to John Vaughan, October 20, 1835.
  - Letter to William Vaughan, Undated; Royal Institution of Great Britain.
  - Rules governing membership., Undated; 8x5; Society of the Cincinnati
  - Table to assist in indentification of the stars, Undated; American Philosophical Society.
  - Tables of logarithms, Undated; American Philosophical Society.
  - Letter to John Vaughan, Undated; 9x7; Ticknor, George, 1791-1871
    Philadelphia. A.L.S. 1p. and add. Introducing George S. Hillard.
  - Bills paid by John Vaughan for the University [of Pennsylvania, Philadelphia], Undated; 7 3/4" x 10"; Vaughan, John, 1756-1841
    n.d. 1 p. and endorsement. D. Unsigned. List of nineteen bills totaling £52.7.6., paid by John Vaughan for building of Philosophical Hall.
  - Concerning American philosophical society communications., Undated; 8-1/2x7-1/2; Vaughan, John, 1756-1841
    D. 1p. Contains also copies of letters from B.Vaughan to Rush; 1782, and A.Hamilton to H.Laurens; Sept. 1780.
  - List of publications on mineralogy presented to the APS., Undated; 13x8; Vaughan, John, 1756-1841
    A.D. 2p. This was originally part of a scrap book kept by J.Vaughan, which contained: T.P.Smith. List of minerals...; June-Nov. 1800 [1801].
  - Letter to ----., Undated; 12x7-1/2; Vaughan, John, 1756-1841
    A.L.S. 1p. and end. List of deficiencies in the Transactions of the Institute and French Academy.
  - Memorandum concerning books., Undated; 12x8; Vaughan, John, 1756-1841
    A.D. 1p. and end.
  - Windmill sketches, Undated; American Philosophical Society.
  - Resolution of the Council...for the centennial celebrarion of the Constitution., Undated; American Philosophical Society.
  - Letter to Persifor Frazer, Undated; 8x5; Bache, Richard Meade
    A.L.S. 3p. With regard to the Franklin Institute publication. Jan. 26
  - Statement of cash paid out, without checks, Undated; 12-1/2x8; Ord, George, 1781-1866
    A.D. 1p.and end. Jan. 28-Nov. 10
  - Letter to John Vaughan, Undated; 7 7/8" x 10 1/8"; Barton, Thomas Pennant, 1803-1869
    ----, ----. 1 p. and address. A.L.S. Is sending some books to the A.P.S. which may have been borrowed from it by his father (Benjamin Smith Barton). April 12
  - Letter to John Vaughan, Undated; 4 7/8" x 7 11/16"; Holbrook, John Edwards, 1794-1871
    [Philadelphia], ----. 1p. and address. A.L.S. Thanks Mr. Vaughan for his kindness. Must take two volumes of Herpetology with him to have additional plates put in. June 2
  - Letter to Dr. [Benjamin] Rush, Undated; 4 1/2" x 7 1/2"; Vaughan, John, 1756-1841
    A.L.S. 1p. and add. Request for certain medical theses. July 26
  - Letter to John Vaughan, Philadelphia, Undated; 10x8; Morelli, Chevalier Domenico de
    A.L.S. 1p. and add. Forwards volumes. Aug. 15
  - Letter to John Vaughan, Undated; Oakford, I. S. (Joshua L. ?)
  - Letter to John Vaughan, Undated; 5" x 8"; Hodgson, William Brown, 1800-1871
    [Philadelphia], ----- Returns Shaw's Travels. Requests permission to borrow other designated books from the A.P.S library. November 10
  - Letter to John Vaughan, Undated; 8x5; Bache, A. D. (Alexander Dallas), 1806-1867
    Monday: A.L.S. 1p. and add. Concerning books borrowed. Nov. 12
  - Letter to [Charles B.] Trego, Undated; 4 3/8" x 7"; Kane, John K. (John Kintzing), 1795-1858
    ----, Friday afternoon, ----. 1 p. A.L.S. Is prevented from attending an [A.P.S.] meeting by the sickness of a friend. December 4
  - Letter to John Vaughan, Undated; 8x5; Short, William, 1759-1849
    Monday. A.L.S. 2p.and add. Concerning the health of Jefferson and his plans for the University of Virginia.
  - Letter to John Vaughan, Undated; 7-1/2x9-1/2; Aitken, Robert, 1735-1802
    Thursday. A.L.S. 1p.and add. Concerning printing for the society. Refers to imperfections in some items of B.Franklin's. FILM 54-64 FRAME 200
  - Letter to [John Vaughan?], Undated; 8x5; Perkins, Thomas Handasyd, 1764-1854
    Friday. A.L.S. 1p. Wishes him to call. On the back is a list of purchases in J. Vaughan's hand.
  - Letter to J[oh]n Vaughan, Undated; 8x5; Cutbush, James, 1788-1823
    Saturday morning. A.L.S. 1p. Forwards volume.
  - Letter to the [American Philosophical Society, Philadelphia], Undated; 7 7/8" x 8 1/16"; Aitken, Robert, 1735-1802
    n. d. 1 p. D. Robert Aitken acknowledges American Philosophical Society as owner of designated copies of Transactions, held subject to their order.
  - Helen Abbott Michael, Undated; Michael, Helen Abbott, 1857-1904
    Mrs.Helen Cecilia de Silver Abbott.
    Not found 6/2011
  - Rules & statutes... together with a list of the fellows & corresponding members., Undated; 8" x 13"; American Society, Held at Philadelphia for Promoting Useful Knowledge
    Ms. D. [11p.] Cover title: Rules of American society. Signature book, 1758. Film copy from photostat in the Historical society of Pennsylvania. Not found 6/2011.
  - Letter to Dr. [John L.] Leconte; [1877]., Undated; 8x5-1/2; Ames, Mary Lesley, 1854-1929
    A.L.S.:Mary Lesley. 1p.and enc. Refers E.D.Copels letter. Enclosure is pencil sketch of plate for Cope's paper on paleontology. On same sheet as letter from Cope to J.P.Lesley, May 5 1877. Not found 6/2011.
  - American philosophical society, Building Committee, Undated; American Philosophical Society. Committee on Extended Accommodations
  - Minute., Undated; 8x4-1/2; American Philosophical Society. Historical and literary committee
    D. 1p. On same sheet as report of committee...; [July 21, 1815]. Not found 6/2011.
  - List of models in the A.P.S collections, Undated; 11x8-1/2; American Philosophical Society. Curators
    D. 3p. Numbered 4a-4c. Not found 6/2011.
  - List of scientific instruments in the A.P.S. collections, Undated; 11x8-1/2; American Philosophical Society. Curators
    D. 4p. Numbered 5a-5c. Not found 6/2011.
  - Rough list of photographs, lithographs, etc., found in the Library of the A.P.S., Undated; 11x8-1/2; American Philosophical Society. Curators
    D. 4p. Page 4: Index reference to photographs mentioned in the Proceedings. Not found 6/2011.
  - Rough list of prints, engravings, crayons, and Daguerrotypes noticed in the Proceedings and Transactions of the A.P.S., Undated; 11x8-1/2; American Philosophical Society. Curators
    D. 6p. Not found 6/2011.
  - Author index to catalogue of the American Philosophical Society library, 1863-64, Undated; American Philosophical Society.
  - Letter to [William Barton], Undated; 9" x 14 3/4"; Barton, Richard Peters, d. 1821
    Mount Airy, Virginia, n. d. 3 pp. and endorsements. Com. Unsigned. Extract only. Method of cultivating cotton in Virginia. Communicated to A.P.S. by William Barton. Read, October 19, 1787. See Pro., XXII, pt. 3, 155.
    Not found 6/2011.
  - Letters acknowledging election., Undated; Boucher de Perthes, M. (Jacques), 1788-1868 American Philosophical Society
    D. 6 vols. Various sizes. For letter from above,see: Vol. I, 1840-1873, p.222
  - Concerning the simoon., Undated; 7-1/2x6; Bruce, James
    D.2p. (see Ms.Comm.to the APS. Natural philosophy, vol. 1, no. 2.)
  - Receipt to B. H. Latrobe., Undated; 3x7; Chesapeake and Delaware Canal Company
    D. 1p. (see Ms.Comm.to the APS. Trade, navigation, etc., no. 29.) This is located between pages 6-7 of translation of Tousard: An inquiry... of proving...cannons; Jan. 4, 1802.
  - Paper on John Fitch, Undated; 8 1/2" x 11"; Cheyney, Edward Potts, 1861-1947
    inventor of the steamboat, and the American philosophical society. T.D. 5 leaves. Abstract of paper read at the general meeting of the A.P.S., April 24, 1937; cf. Year Book, 1937,p.48. Contains ms. corrections. Not found 6/2011.
  - Letter to [the American philosophical society]., Undated; 10x8; Dannery, S.
    L.in 3rd.p. 1p.and end. In French. (see Ms.comm.to the APS. Natural history, vol. 2, no. 84.) Concerning lichens.
  - Minutes of the American Philosophical Society, Undated; American Philosophical Society.
    See Minutes under date of Jan. 4, 1833. Printed: Hazard Register...;vol.14,190.
  - Minutes of the American Philosophical Society, Undated; American Philosophical Society.
    See Minutes, Oct. 19, 1827, for reference to this letter. Presented by Mrs. John F. Lewis from Mr. Lewis's library, Dec. 1937. Not found 6/2011.
  - Concerning specifications of his discovery on steam-engines., Undated; 9-1/2x8; Evans, Oliver, 1755-1819
    D. 2p.and end. Extract. (see Ms.Comm. to the APS. Mechanics, Machinery, Eng., etc., no. 29b.) Not found 6/2011.
  - Queries for the Austrian traveler destined to visit Arabia, Undated; 8x6-1/2; Fothergill, A. (Anthony), 1732?-1813
    Persia, etc. D. 2p.and end. (see Ms.comm.to the APS. Philology, literature, etc., vol. 2, no. 67.) Not found 6/2011.
  - Über die "sprache" und die orientierung der bienen., Undated; 11 1/2" x 8"; Frisch, Karl von, 1886-1982
    T.D. 6 leaves ---- English translation. T.D. 8 leaves and 6 illus. The Magellanic premium was awarded by the APS to Dr. von Frisch for this paper, Nov. 11, 1955. The translation was read before the Society,April 20, 1956, by Donald R. Griffin; printed: APS Proceedings, 100,5,1956. Not found 6/2011.
  - An improved capstan for ships of war., Undated; 15" x 9"; Galvin, J.
    A. sketch S. 1p. Deposited with the A.P.S., Feb. 15, 1811. See Minutes of that date. Not found 6/2011.
  - Letter to [Henry] Phillips, Undated; 9x5-1/2; Hockley, Thomas, 1839-1892
    [1889?]. A.L.S. 1p. Says he would like to propose S.D. McConnell for membership in Society.
  - Letters acknowledging election., Undated; Hockley, Thomas, 1839-1892 American Philosophical Society
    D. 6 vols. Various sizes. For letter from above, see: Vol. II, 1874-1888, p. 249
  - Certificates of membership, Undated; Hodge, Hugh, ca. 1755-1798 American Philosophical Society
    signed by various presidents, and listed herein by date and presidental signature. For additional data, see main card. Hugh Hodge was elected Jan. 15, 1796.
  - Description of a spring block designed to assist vessels in sailing [ca.1787]., Undated; 13x8; Hopkinson, Francis, 1737-1791
    Copy of D. 2p. Printed: APS Trans.,III,331-333. This won the Magellanic premium for 1790.
  - Particulars of the New Brunswick tornado., Undated; 7 7/8" x 9 3/4"; Janeway, J. J. (Jacob Jones), 1774-1858
    New Brunswick, [N.J.] April 23, 1936. 14 pp. A.Com. S. Read. May 20, 1836, See Pro., XXII, pt. 3, 687. Not found 6/2011.
  - Table of gravity and strength of timber in India., Undated; 8 1/4" x 13"; Jones, William, of Calcutta
    ----, n.d. 2 pp. and endorsement. Com. Read. June 17, 1808. See Pro., XXII, pt. 3, 407.
  - Answers to seventeen queries propounded by William Jones of Philadelphia., Undated; 8 1/8" x 10 3/8"; Jones, William, of Calcutta
    ----, n.d. 5 pp. and endorsement. Com. Begins at p. 4, pp. 1-3 missing. Read, June 17, 1808. See Pro., XXII, pt. 3, 407.
  - Child maintenance at public expense., Undated; 8 1/2" x 13"; Kane, Elisha Kent, 1856-1935
    Typed D. 3 leaves. Read before the American philosophical society, Nov. 7, 1919.
  - Is western civilization disintegrating or reconstructing?, Undated; 8 1/2" x 11"; Kroeber, A. L. (Alfred Louis), 1876-1960
    Typed D. [1] 14 leaves Original ms. of paper read by author before APS, Oct. 27,1950. Printed: APS Proceedings, 95,no.2
  - Letter to the American philosophical society., Undated; 10x8; L., A. F.
    L. 3p. In German. (see Ms. comm. to the APS. Philology, literature, etc., vol. 2, no. 40.)
  - Letter to [the American philosophical society?]., Undated; 9-1/2x8; L., A. F.
    L. 1p. In German. (see Ms.comm.to the APS. Philology, literature, etc., vol. 2, no. 40a.) Not found 6/2011.
  - Some observations concerning longitude., Undated; 12x8; Laurie, Robert
    D.S. 3p. and end. (in B.Franklin's hand ?) and other hand. (see Ms.Comm.to APS. Math and Astronomy, vol. 1, no. 8.)
  - Précis d'un ouvrage sur les hospitaux., Undated; 12x8; LeRoy, John Jean-Baptiste, ca. 1724-1800
    A.D. 26p. (see Ms.Comm.to APS. Medicine, anatomy & physiology, no.1.) Refers to B.Franklin.
  - Letter to Ella [M.] Morrison [sic; Phila., 1898?], Undated; 6-1/2x5; McKean, W. V. (William Vincent), 1820-1902
    A.L.S. 1p. Concerns Finance Committee. Refers to Tatham. Not found 6/2011.
  - The conservation of horses in war., Undated; 8 1/2" x 11"; Marshall, Clarence James, 1864-1938
    Typed D. 10 leaves. Read before the A.P.S., Nov.3, 1916. See letter from Amos P. Brown, to Dr. Hays, Dec. 10, 1916, relative to publication of paper. Not found 6/2011.
  - Letter to [Samuel Latham ?] Mitchill;[ca. 1816]., Undated; Mathieu, Charles Leopold
    Newspaper clipping. 2 columns. (see APS. Historical...committee letterbooks, tipped in at the front of vol. 1.) Comparative philology of the Chinese and Atlantan languages. Not found 6/2011.
  - Dissertation on disease occasioned by bite of a mad dog, by Dr. Mease., Undated; Mease, James, 1771-1846. 5-16-1795
    See Pro. XXII, pt. 3, 232, June 19, 1795. Not found 6/2011.
  - Concerning an offer of a marble copy of the zodiac of Denderah, Undated; 9-1/2x7-1/2; Michaux, François André, 1770-1855
    Egypt. Printed D. with ms.note,S. 2p.and end. In French. (see Ms. comm. to the APS. Philology, literature, etc., vol. 1, no. 20.) Not found 6/2011.
  - Letter to ---, Undated
    Recat. as Mag 23, 1833. Enc 11 Jan 1982 Not found 6/2011.
  - Letters acknowledging election., Undated; Morton, Henry J. (Henry Jackson), 1807-1890
    D. 6 vols. Various sizes. For letter from above, see: Vol. 1, 1840-1873, p.181.
  - Report of Committee, Undated; American Philosophical Society.
    For report of committee, see: Report of Committee...: Feb. 13, 1805.
  - Discours sur cette question:, Undated; Nassy, David de Isaac Cohen, 1747-1806
    les savantes récherches des botanistes - modernes, ont elles produit plus vu moins d'utilite, pour le genre humain en général, que les récherches des anciens que se bornoient à la seule découverte des proprietés des plantes? Avec l'histoire de la découverte et les vertus du Tikimma plante de Surinam et de la Guiane. Phila., Feb.20, 1794. Nassy, David. Discours... A.D.S. [2] 15,2p. 2 col.p1. In French. Presented to the Society,Feb. 1794; cf. Minutes of Feb. 21 and March 21,1794. Photo. of plates and t.p. and pp.1-2. FILM 403 FRAME9-5
  - Receipt No.354 for a collection of 24 bronze medals...described on accompanying list., Undated; 8-1/2x5; Pennsylvania Museum and School of Industrial Art
    Printed form filled in in MS., S.: Dalton Dorr 2p.
  - Concerning cholera., Undated; 12x8-1/2; Percente, Francesco
    A.D.S. with initials. 2p. In Spanish. (see Ms. Comm. to the APS. Medicine, anatomy and physiology, no.58.)
  - Tendencies in the national development of waterways and water traffic, Undated; 8 1/2" x 11"; Schoff, Wilfred H. (Wilfred Harvey), 1874-1932
    with reminiscences of the service rendered by the American philosophical society in behalf of early canal construction in America. Typed D. 41 [i.e.45] leaves. Read before the American philosophical society, April 4, 1919.
  - Letters to ----, Undated; Schuyler, Peter, 1657-1724
    Albany, Feb 18, 1706/7: Aug. 11, 1797: and Aug. 29, 1720. See Antiquarian Bookman; March 25, 1950. p.979.
  - Letter to president of A.P.S., Undated; 11x8-1/2; Société de géographie (France)
    Paris, Sept. 18, 1874. L.S.:[B] de la Roncière le Noury, president. 2p.,end. In French. Invites Society to the Congrès international des sciences géographiques. Forwards documents.
  - The preglacial outlet of the upper Ohio river into the Erie basin., Undated; Spencer, J. W.
    n.d. 5pp. 8 3/8" x 10 3/8". Com. Communicated by Mr. Lesley. April 15, 1881. See Pro., XIX, 353.
  - [Upon the advantages of an universal language]., Undated; Steiner, P.
    Darmstadt, August 22, 1888. 15 pp. and endorsements. 8 1/4" x 13". A.Com.S. See minutes, November 2, 1888, in Pro., XXV, 303. Not found 6/2011.
  - Letter to Prof. J. P. Lesley, Undated; Stevenson, John J. (John James), 1841-1924
    New York, Oct. 21, 1884. A.L.S. 1p.,end. 11x8-1/2. Discusses map for his article on the geology of Virginia. Not found 6/2011.
  - Estate of David Rittenhouse, Undated; Thomson, Peter. 10-24-1796
    A piece of ground, part of the estate of David Rittenhouse, in trust for a burial ground.
  - Concerning a possible discovery of an effectual prevention against phthisis pulmonalis., Undated; 12-1/2x8; Whitehead, John C.
    D.S. 4p. (see Ms. Comm. to the APS. Medicine, anatomy and physiology, no. 57.) Not found 6/2011.
  - Letter to John Vaughan, Undated; 7-1/2x5-1/2; Wistar, Caspar, 1761-1818
    Saturday noon. A.L.S. 2p.,end. and add. (see Ms.comm.to the APS. Natural philosophy, vol. 2, no. 94.) Concerning revising Mr. Curson's paper on the barometer and hygrometer. Not found 6/2011.
  - Manuscript archives of the Wistar association., Undated; Wistar Association
    v.1 F. n.t-p. 1818-1910 (?) 1835-1908 Binder's title. Not found 6/2011.
  - Letter to Miss Morrison [sic, Ella M. Morison], Undated; 5-1/2x4; Phillips, Ellen
    A.L.S. 2p. Will call soon at A.P.S. for promised photographs. Sept. 30. Not found 6/2011.